is not true. With age comes the veneer of respectability and a veneer of uncomfortable truths. But what was true was that my parents, my mother, and my father went along with it, did not trust the state to educate me. So listen to how I sound. They determined that they would send me to a private school, but my father worked at Vauxhall Motors. It's quite difficult to fund a private school education and feed his army of children. I remember going on to the school for the entrance exam, and my father said to the priest — it was a Catholic school — he wanted a better "heducation" for the boy, but also, he, my father, never even managed to pass worms, never mind entrance exams. But in order to fund my education, he was going to have to do some dodgy stuff, so my father would fund my education by trading in illicit goods from the back of his car, and that was made even more tricky because my father, that's not his car by the way. My father aspired to have a car like that, but my father had a beaten-up Mini, and he never, being a Jamaican coming to this country, he never had a driving license, he never had any insurance or road tax or MOT. He thought, "I know how to drive; why do I need the state's validation?" But it became a little tricky when we were stopped by the police, and we were stopped a lot by the police, and I was impressed by the way that my father dealt with the police. He would promote the policeman immediately, so that P.C. Bloggs became Detective Inspector Bloggs in the course of the conversation and wave us on merrily. So my father was exhibiting what we in Jamaica called "playing fool to catch wise." But it lent also an idea that actually he was being diminished or belittled by the policeman — as a 10-year-old boy, I saw that — but also there was an ambivalence towards authority. So on the one hand, there was a mocking of authority, but on the other hand, there was a deference towards authority, and these Caribbean people had an overbearing obedience towards authority, which is very striking, very strange in a way, because migrants are very courageous people. They leave their homes. My father and my mother left Jamaica and they traveled 4,000 miles, and yet they were infantilized by travel. They were timid, and somewhere along the line, the natural order was reversed. The children became the parents to the parent. The Caribbean people came to this country with a five-year plan: they would work, some money, and then go back, but the five years became 10, the 10 became 15, and before you know it, you're changing the wallpaper, and at that point, you know you're here to stay. Although there's still the kind of temporariness that our parents felt about being here, but we children knew that the game was up. I think there was a feeling that they would not be able to continue with the ideals of the life that they expected. The reality was very much different. And also, that was true of the reality of trying to educate me. Having started the process, my father did not continue. It was left to my mother to educate me, and as George Lamming would say, it was my mother who fathered me. Even in his absence, that old mantra remained: You are being watched. But such ardent watchfulness can lead to anxiety, so much so that years later, when I was investigating why so many young black men were diagnosed with schizophrenia, six times more than they ought to be, I was not surprised to hear the psychiatrist say, "Black people are schooled in paranoia." And I wonder what Bageye would make of that. Now I also had a 10-year-old son, and turned my attention to Bageye and I went in search of him. He was back in Luton, he was now 82, and I hadn't seen him for 30-odd years, and when he opened the door, I saw this tiny little man with lambent, smiling eyes, and he was smiling, and I'd never seen him smile. I was very disconcerted by that. But we sat down, and he had a Caribbean friend with him, talking some old time talk, and my father would look at me, and he looked at me as if I would miraculously disappear as I had arisen. And he turned to his friend, and he said, "This boy and me have a deep, deep connection, deep, deep connection." But I never felt that connection. If there was a pulse, it was very weak or hardly at all. And I almost felt in the course of that reunion that I was auditioning to be my father's son. When the book came out, it had fair reviews in the national papers, but the paper of choice in Luton is not The Guardian, it's the Luton News, and the Luton News ran the headline about the book, "The Book That May Heal a 32-Year-Old Rift." And I understood that could also represent the rift between one generation and the next, between people like me and my father's generation, but there's no tradition in Caribbean life of memoirs or biographies. It was a tradition that you didn't chat about your business in public. But I welcomed that title, and I thought actually, yes, there is a possibility that this will open up conversations that we'd never had before. This will close the generation gap, perhaps. This could be an instrument of repair. And I even began to feel that this book may be perceived by my father as an act of filial devotion. Poor, deluded fool. Bageye was stung by what he perceived to be the public airing of his shortcomings. He was stung by my betrayal, and he went to the newspapers the next day and demanded a right of reply, and he got it with the headline "Bageye Bites Back." And it was a coruscating account of my betrayal. I was no son of his. He recognized in his mind that his colors had been dragged through the mud, and he couldn't allow that. He had to restore his dignity, and he did so, and initially, although I was disappointed, I grew to admire that stance. There was still fire bubbling through his veins, even though he was 82 years old. And if it meant that we would now return to 30 years of silence, my father would say, "If it's so, then it's so." Jamaicans will tell you that there's no such thing as facts, there are only versions. We all tell ourselves the versions of the story that we can best live with. Each generation builds up an edifice which they are reluctant or sometimes unable to disassemble, but in the writing, my version of the story began to change, and it was detached from me. I lost my hatred of my father. I did no longer want him to die or to murder him, and I felt free, much freer than I'd ever felt before. And I wonder whether that freedness could be transferred to him. In that initial reunion, I was struck by an idea that I had very few photographs of myself as a young child. This is a photograph of me, nine months old. In the original photograph, I'm being held up by my father, Bageye, but when my parents separated, my mother excised him from all aspects of our lives. She took a pair of scissors and cut him out of every photograph, and for years, I told myself the truth of this photograph was that you are alone, you are unsupported. But there's another way of looking at this photograph. This is a photograph that has the potential for a reunion, a potential to be reunited with my father, and in my yearning to be held up by my father, I held him up to the light. In that first reunion, it was very awkward and tense moments, and to lessen the tension, we decided to go for a walk. And as we walked, I was struck that I had reverted to being the child even though I was now towering above my father. I was almost a foot taller than my father. He was still the big man, and I tried to match his step. And I realized that he was walking as if he was still under observation, but I admired his walk. He walked like a man on the losing side of the F.A. Cup Final
no es cierto. Con la edad viene la apariencia de respetabilidad y una apariencia de verdades incómodas. Pero lo que era cierto era que mis padres, mi madre, y mi padre estaban de acuerdo en no confiar mi educación al estado. Así que escuchen. Decidieron que me enviarían a una escuela privada, pero mi padre trabajaba en Vauxhall Motors. Era bastante difícil de financiar una escuela privada y alimentar a su ejército de niños. Recuerdo que fui a la escuela para el examen de ingreso y mi padre dijo al sacerdote —era una escuela católica— que quería una mejor "jeducación" para el niño, pero, él, mi padre, ni siquiera logró pasar virus, y mucho menos los exámenes de ingreso. Pero para financiar mi educación, tendría que hacer algunas cosas dudosas, así que mi padre pagaría mi educación comerciando con bienes ilícitos de la parte trasera del auto, lo que fue aún más difícil porque el auto no era de mi padre, por cierto. Mi padre aspiraba a tener un auto así, pero mi padre tenía un mini abollado y nunca, siendo un jamaicano inmigrado a este país, tuvo permiso de conducir, nunca tuvo ningún tipo de seguro, impuesto de circulación o ITV. Pensó: "Yo sé conducir; ¿por qué necesito la validación del estado?" Pero se hizo un poco difícil cuando nos detuvo la policía, y la policía nos detuvo muchas veces, y me impresionó la forma en que mi padre trataba con la policía. Ascendía al policía inmediatamente, por lo que el policía Bloggs se convertía en el Inspector criminalista Bloggs en el transcurso de la conversación. y nos despedía alegremente con la mano. Así que mi padre desplegaba lo que en Jamaica se llama "hacerse el tonto para pillar como listo". Pero también reafirmaba la idea de que en realidad estaba discriminado o menospreciado por la policía, —como niño de 10 años, lo veía— pero también existía una ambivalencia hacia la autoridad. Así, por un lado, había una burla de la autoridad, pero por otro lado, había una deferencia hacia la autoridad, y estos pueblos del Caribe tienen una obediencia exagerada hacia la autoridad, que es muy llamativo, muy extraño, porque los inmigrantes son personas muy valientes. Dejan sus casas. Mi padre y mi madre dejaron Jamaica y viajaron unos 6500 km, y, sin embargo, el viaje les infantilizó. Eran tímidos, y, en algún lugar, a lo largo de la línea, el orden natural se invirtió. Los niños se convirtieron en los padres de los padres. Las personas del Caribe llegaron a este país con un plan de 5 años: iban a trabajar, ganar algo de dinero, y luego volver, pero los cinco años se convirtieron en 10, los 10 se convirtieron en 15, y antes de darse cuenta, estás cambiando el empapelado de las paredes. En ese punto, uno sabe que está aquí para quedarse. Aunque aún exista la clase de temporalidad que nuestros padres sentían por estar aquí, pero nosotros, los niños sabíamos que el juego había terminado. Creo que había una sensación de que que no podrían continuar con los ideales de la vida que ellos esperaban. La realidad era muy diferente. Y también, era cierta la realidad de tratar de educarme. Después de haber iniciado el proceso, mi padre no continuó. Dejó a mi madre que me educara, y como George Lamming diría, fue mi madre quien me engendró. Incluso, en su ausencia, ese viejo mantra se mantuvo: Te están vigilando. Pero esa vigilancia ardiente puede llevar a la ansiedad, tanto es así que años más tarde, cuando yo estaba investigando por qué a tantos jóvenes negros se les diagnosticó esquizofrenia, 6 veces más de lo que deberían ser, no me sorprendió escuchar al psiquiatra decir: "Los negros son educados en la paranoia". Y me pregunto qué diría Bageye al respecto. Ahora al tener también un hijo de 10 años, torné mi atención a Bageye y fui en su búsqueda. Estaba de nuevo en Luton, tenía ahora de 82 años, y yo no lo había visto desde hacía unos 30 años, y cuando abrió la puerta, vi a este pequeño hombre pequeño con ojos ondulantes y sonrientes, y sonreía, y yo nunca antes lo había visto sonreír. Eso me desconcertó mucho. Pero nos sentamos, y él estaba con un amigo del Caribe, hablando de viejos tiempos, y mi padre me miraba, y él me miró como si yo fuera a desaparecer milagrosamente tal y como había aparecido. Y él se volvió hacia su amigo y le dijo: "Este chico y yo tenemos una conexión profunda, profunda, una conexión profunda, profunda". Pero nunca sentí esa conexión. Si había un pulso, era muy débil o apenas nada. Y en el transcurso de esa reunión casi me sentí que hacia una audición para ser el hijo de mi padre. Cuando salió el libro, obtuve buenas críticas en los periódicos nacionales, pero el periódico preferido en Luton no es The Guardian, es el Luton News, y el Luton News publicó el titular sobre el libro, "El libro que puede curar una desavenencia de un chico de 32 años". Y comprendí que también podía representar la ruptura entre una generación y la siguiente, entre la gente como yo y la generación de mi padre, pero no hay tradición en la vida del Caribe de memorias o biografías. Era tradición el no conversar sobre las cosas de uno en público. Pero di la bienvenida a ese título, y pensé que en realidad, sí, hay una posibilidad de que esto abriera conversaciones que nunca habíamos tenido antes. Esto cerrará la brecha generacional, tal vez. Esto podría ser un instrumento de reparación. Y yo ni siquiera empecé a sentir que este libro pudiera ser percibidos por mi padre como un acto de devoción filial. Pobre, tonto engañado. A Bageye le picó lo que él percibió como la difusión pública de sus defectos. Se sintió herido por mi traición, y al día siguiente se fue al periódico y exigió el derecho de réplica, y lo consiguió con el titular "Bageye contraataca". Y era una cuestión pendiente a mi traición. Ya no era hijo suyo. Reconoció en su mente que su reputación había sido arrastrada por el suelo, y no lo podía permitir. Tenía que recuperar su dignidad, y así lo hizo, y en un principio, aunque estaba decepcionado, llegué a admirar esa postura. Todavía había llamas chispeando en sus venas, a pesar de que tenía 82 años. Y si eso significaba que ahora volveríamos a 30 años de silencio, mi padre decía: "Si es así, entonces es así". Los jamaicanos dicen que no existe nada más que los hechos, solo hay versiones. Todos nos contamos versiones de la historia con las que podemos vivir mejor. Cada generación construye un edificio que no está dispuesta o no puede a veces desmontar, pero en la escritura, mi versión de la historia comenzó a cambiar, y se separa de mí. Perdí el odio a mi padre. Yo ya no quiero que se muera o asesinarle, y me sentí libre, mucho más libre de lo que nunca antes me había sentido. Y me pregunto si esa libertad se le podría transmitir a él. En esa reunión inicial, me llamó la atención una cosa que tenía muy pocas fotografías mías, siendo un niño pequeño. Esta es una fotografía mía, tenía nueve meses. En la fotografía original, me sostenía mi padre, Bageye, pero al separarse mis padres, mi madre lo extirpó de todos los aspectos de nuestras vidas. Ella tomó las tijeras y lo recortó de cada fotografía, y durante años, me dije que la verdad de esta fotografía era que yo estaba solo, que no tenía apoyo. Pero hay otra forma de ver esta fotografía. Esta es una fotografía con el potencial para una reunión, un potencial para reunirse con mi padre, y en mi anhelo de que mi padre me sostuviera, salió él a la luz. En esa primera reunión, hubo momentos muy difíciles y tensos, y para disminuir la tensión, decidimos ir a dar un paseo. Y mientras caminábamos, me llamó la atención que yo había vuelto a ser el niño a pesar de que ser ya más alto que mi padre. Yo era unos 30 cm más alto que mi padre. Para mí seguía siendo el hombre grande, y traté de igualar su paso. Y me di cuenta de que caminaba como si todavía estuviera vigilado, pero yo admiraba su paso. Caminaba como un hombre en el lado de los perdedores de la final de la copa
mounting the steps to collect his condolence medal. There was dignity in defeat. Thank you. (Applause)
dando los pasos para recoger la medalla de consolación. Hubo dignidad en la derrota. Gracias. (Aplausos)